Guide to the Jefferson School of Social Science (New York, N.Y.) Records and Indexes TAM.005
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Jefferson School of Social Science Records and Indexes
1931-1958
1944-1955
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Jefferson School of Social Science (New York, N.Y.)
Rand School of Social Science
TAM.005
8 Linear Feet (3 boxes and 11 card trays)
The Jefferson School of Social Science (1943-1956) was a Marxist adult education institute in New York City associated with the Communist Party, USA. Among the faculty were a number of leftist academics dismissed from the City University of New York, including the school's director, Howard Selsam. It had as many as 5000 students enrolled per term, but the Subversive Activities Control Board forced its closing in 1956. The school published course-related pamphlets and its Librarian, Henry Black, accumulated a 30,000 volume library. The collection consists of Jefferson School materials, course outlines and related readings, bibliographies, pamphlets published by the school, unpublished typescripts, and material from the Workers School and from the Communist Party. It also includes the original indexes to the Jefferson School Library's periodical and pamphlet holdings.
Custodial History
Collection was part of the Rand School Archives, and may have been donated by Henry Black, the Jefferson School's librarian. In 1963 the collection was transferred to the Tamiment Library by members of the People's Education Camp Society, Inc. The accession number associated with this collection is 1963.010
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
The Jefferson School of Social Science (1943-1956) was a Marxist adult education institute in New York City. Like its predecessor, the Workers School (1923-1943), it was associated with the Communist Party, USA. The school occupied a nine story building at 575 Sixth Avenue, offered hundreds of courses to as many as 5000 students each term, and published course-related pamphlets. Librarian Henry Black accumulated a 30,000 volume library, and compiled course-related bibliographies. Among the faculty were a number of leftist academics dismissed from the City University of New York, including the school's director, Howard Selsam. The courses ranged from the year-long Institute of Marxist Studies to cultural and self-improvement offerings. The Subversive Activities Control Board's designation of the school as a Communist-controlled organization, led to the closing of the school in the fall of 1956.
Scope and Content Note
Series I principally consists of Jefferson School materials, but also contains some material from the Workers School and from the Communist Party, and includes course outlines and related readings, bibliographies, pamphlets published by the school, unpublished typescripts, correspondence and unpublished writings of Henry Black, speeches by William Z. Foster, including several given along with William F. Dunne in 1931 at the Workers School's National Training School (for Communist Party cadre), student scrapbooks (steel strike, 1949), pamphlets and briefs concerning the Subversive Activities Control Board's decision to list the school as a Communist-front organization, and a file of Communist Party Farm Commission minutes and other documents from 1946. The authored pamphlets include works by Herbert Aptheker, Howard Selsam and Doxey A. Wilkerson. Unpublished writings include Henry Black's book-length Fundamentals of Subject Cataloging, A Guide to Marxist Studies (a bibliographical introduction) by the editorial board of Science & Society, and The Seattle General Strike of 1919, an apparently contemporaneous participants' account. There is also an incomplete set of the Library Service to Labor Newsletter (ALA), 1949-1954.
Series II contains the following seven indexes (on 3x5 card files) to the Jefferson School Library's periodical and pamphlet holdings (with the bulk of the entries covering the years 1944-1955): Earl Browder Articles, 1922-1944; Pamphlets; Periodicals; Poems; Portraits (Photographs); Reviews (Drama, Motion Pictures); Short Stories.
Arrangement
Organized into two series, each arranged alphabetically: I. Records; II. Indexes to Jefferson School Library Periodicals and Pamphlets.
Folders are arranged alphabetically by subject/author heading within each series.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
The William Francis Dunne Papers (Tamiment 145)
The Francis Franklin Marxist Historical-Philosophical Manuscripts (Tamiment 182)
* Jefferson School of Social Science. Records, 1942-1956. One reel of microfilm. (* at the State Historical Society of Wisconsin, Archives Division).
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transfer from the Rand School Archives, 1963. Probably donated thereto by Henry Black, the Jefferson School librarian. The accession number associated with this collection is 1963.010
Correspondence.; Pamphlets.; Scrapbooks.; Typescripts.; New York (N.Y.); Communism -- United States.; General Strike, Seattle, Wash., 1919.; Right and left (Political science); Subject cataloging |x Handbooks, manuals, etc.; Adult education -- New York (State) -- New York.; Aptheker, Herbert, 1915-2003.; Communist Party of the United States of America. Farm Commission; Davis, Benjamin J. (Benjamin Jefferson), 1903-1964; Black, Henry. Fundamentals of subject cataloging.; Selsam, Howard, 1903-; Wilkerson, Doxey Alphonso, 1905-1993.; Foster, William Z., 1881-1961.; Dunne, William Francis, 1887-1953.; United States. Subversive Activities Control Board; Jefferson School of Social Science (New York, N.Y.); Rand School of Social Science
- Series I. Records
  - AFL-CIO Merger Convention, Excerpts from Resolutions; March 1, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - All-School Self-Critical Conference, Report; February 21, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - American History Course Outlines, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Ancient Mediterranean World Course Outline, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Annual Reports, 1945-1947 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Aptheker, Herbert: American Imperialism and White Chauvinism, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Aptheker, Herbert: The Constitution of the United States, ca.1954 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Aptheker, Herbert: The Declaration of Independence, ca.1954 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Associated Farmers, Inc.: A Brief Summary (California anti-labor group); July 6, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Balamuth, Louis: Atomic Power: Its History and Future, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Black, Henry: Articles (unpublished ts): Agricultural Policy; Documentation; Indexing Costs, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Black, Henry: Bibliographies, Readers Advisory, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Black, Henry: Correspondence, 1944-1958 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Black, Henry: Education Articles (unpublished ts), undated, 1957-1958 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Black, Henry: Fundamentals of Subject Cataloging (unpublished, book-length typescript); May 4, 1905, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Black, Henry: Fundamentals of Subject Cataloging - Outline, Research Notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Black, Henry: Miscellaneous Notes & Unpublished Writings, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Board of Trustees: Statement (announcing closing of the J.S.); November 27, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Capitalism and the Class Struggle, Course Outline, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Children: Conference on Ideological Needs of, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - China: Course Outline, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Coalition Politics and Electoral Problems, Selected Readings: Excerpts from U.S. Marxist Writings on Developments Between 1936 and 1950; October 1, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Communist Manifesto, 100th Anniversary (Forum, Manhattan Center, NY). Includes speeches of William Z. Foster, J.S. Faculty; December 8, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Communist Party and the Struggle for Peace, Democracy, Socialism: Curriculum, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Communist Party USA, Cooperative Research Project on the Theory and Practice of ("... to assemble.. .information and...analyses.. .for the legal defense of the several CP members facing deportation.. ."], undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Course Descriptions (brief), undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Cultural Departments at the Jefferson School: Some Critical Comments.. .; May 31, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Davis, Benjamin J. Jr.: On the Struggle for Peace and Freedom, ca.1956 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Dunne, William F.: National Training School Lectures (labor topics); May 1, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Economics: Course Outlines, Readings, undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Egypt, Modern: Preliminary Report to Dr. DuBois Seminar; March 2, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Epstein, Irene: A Bibliography on the Negro Woman in the United States, undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Epstein, Irene and Doxey A. Wilkerson: Questions and Answers on the Woman Question; May 6, 1905, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - European History Course Outline, undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Farm Commission, CPUSA: Internal Documents; September 1, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Foster, William Z.: Guide for Study Groups and Self-Study on History of the Communist Party of the United States, Parts I & II, undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Foster, William Z.: National Training School Speeches (labor topics); Apr-May 1931 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Human History Course Outline, undated (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Imperialism, Course Outline, undated (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Imperialism: Course Outlines, undated (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - India and the Middle East: Course Outline, undated (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Intelligence Theory and Practice as a Weapon Against the Negro People, undated (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Jackson, Jim: Forces of Progress in the South; February 1, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Jews: Course Outlines, undated (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Jones, Claudia: An End to the Neglect of the Problems of the Negro Woman! [12 pp.], undated (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Karlson, William: Discussion Manuscript on Child Development (book-length ts, unpublished); Notes on a ms on Child Development... by M.O. [critique], undated (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Korea and United States Imperialism: A Selected List of Recent References; July 1, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Labor Press: Significant Articles, 1936, 1944-1946 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Labor Research Association: Outlines for a History of American Workers, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Labor Research, Reference Guides for (by Francis Gates - Univ of California, Berkeley Library); May 1, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Latin America & Puerto Rico: Course Outlines, Study Materials, undated (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Lawson, Elizabeth: The American Standard of Living, undated (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Leaders of Their People: The Careers of Harriet Tubman, Ida B. Wells-Barnett, Moranda Smith, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 52A)
  - Lenin's Imperialism, Study Guide for, undated (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Library Service to Labor Groups Case Studies 1 & 2 (Newark & Boston Public Libraries, 1948-1949 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Library Service to Labor Newsletter (ALA) - incomplete, 1949-1954 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Makarenko in the Soviet Press, Discussion On, 1950-1951 (issued by the Jefferson School Bookshop), undated (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Marxism: Course Outlines and Related Readings, undated (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Marxism I: Science of Society - Course Outline; Fall 1949 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Marxism II: Elements of Political Economy - Course Outline; Fall 1949 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Marxism Leninism I; April 1, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Marxist Studies, A Guide to ("Bibliographical Introduction" - a book-length typescript, unpublished) - written by the Editorial Board of Science & Society, ca.1937 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Marxist Studies, Institute of: Course Outlines, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Mason, Chick: Sources of Our Dilemma: A Rejection of the Right-Opportunist, Left-Sectarian Explanation by Our Leadership [28 pp]; July 1, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Mathematics and Science: Course Outlines & Related Readings, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Medical Student Seminar: A Critique of the Bourgeois Concepts of Race and Constitution in Classical Medicine [81 pp.]. Presented at the J.S. Conference on Science & the Scientist in the Fight for Peace & Socialism; 23-25 Jun 1950 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous Course Related & Other Mimeographed Reading Material, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Negro Labor Since 1867, a Fact Sheet on; May 5, 1905, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Negro People, 1619-1918, History of...Study Outline; April 22, 1905, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - The Negro Press; A Vital Democratic Heritage [7 pp.], undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Negroes: Course Outlines and Related Readings, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Paxton, Max T. On Comrade Jackson's Report: A Dissent; March 3, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Philosophy Course Outlines & Related Readings, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Philosophy, What Is?: Selectee Readings [48 pp], undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Political Economy I; April 1, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Political Economy I: Wages, Prices & Profits - Course Outline; May 2, 1905, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Political Economy II; April 1, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Political Economy Course Outlines, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Political Economy Lessons 8 & 9 (Abridged) - Economic Crises, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Political Science: Course Outlines, Glossary, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Prago, Albert & George Siskind: Productive & Non-Productive Labor Under Capitalism, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Psychology: Course Outlines, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Railroad Strikes of 1877, 1886 (two typescripts), undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Rozenberg, D.: Outline of Marx's Capital Volumes II & III, undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Russian, Reading, undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - San Francisco and After (J.S. Forum, Town Hall, NY); May 25, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Science Department: Toward an Understanding of the Human Brain, ca.1953 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - The Science of Society: An Introduction to Marxism - Course Outline; May 2, 1905, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Science of Society - Queens-Nassau Annexes of the J.S., undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Seattle General Strike: An Account...Issued by the History Committee of the General Strike Committee [unpublished ts, 37 pp] Note: this appears to be a contemporary account., undated (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Selsam, Howard: The Negro People in the United States: Facts for All Americans; May 6, 1905, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Social Democracy, Bibliography on; May 1, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Soviet Biology: From the Discussion of the Lysenko Report [49 pp], ca.1948 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Soviet Union: Course Outlines and Related Reading, undated (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Spanish, Courses Taught in - Outlines, undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Stalin, Joseph: Study Guide for Economic Problems of Socialism in the USSR, undated (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Stalin on Capitalist Crisis and International Affairs, 1930-1939, undated (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Stalin's Economic Problems: Course Outline, undated (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Steel Strike (1949) - Student Scrapbooks, Bound; May 2, 1905 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Steel Strike (1949) - Student Scrapbooks, Loose; May 2, 1905 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Subversive Activities Control Board Case: Defense Briefs and Campaign Material, 1948-1955 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Subversive Activities Control Board Case: Recommended Decision; December 29, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Titoism: Course Outline; CPUSA Discussion Outline, undated, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Vila, William: Notes on the Puerto Rican Question; May 6, 1905, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Vilner, Meir: The Cold War and the Question of the Yiddish Language in the USSR - Speech at the 13th Congress of the Communist Party of Israel; May 9, 1905, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Vilner, Meir: Marxism, Humanism and Hyman Levy; May 1, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Wallace, Henry: Debate on; May 1, 1905, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Wieden, Peter: The Working Class and the Nation, ca.1939 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Wilkerson, Doxey A.: Class Forces in the Development of Free Public Education in the U.S.; December 1, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Wilkerson, Doxey A.: The Historic Fight to Abolish School Segregation in the United States; May 7, 1905, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Woman Question / Women: Course Outlines, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Zhadanov, A.: The International Situation, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Series II. Indexes to Jefferson School Library Periodicals and Pamphlets
  - Browder, Earl: Articles, 1922-1944 (arranged chronologically) (Box 3, Folder Drawer 1)
  - Pamphlets (by author), undated (Box 3, Folder Drawer 2)
  - Periodicals: Author Index, undated (Box 3, Folder Drawer 3-7)
  - Poems (by author), undated (Box 3, Folder Drawer 8)
  - Portraits, Individuals (photographs), undated (Box 3, Folder Drawer 9)
  - Reviews: a. Drama; b. Motion Pictures (by title), undated (Box 3, Folder Drawer 10)
  - Short Stories (by author), undated (Box 3, Folder Drawer 11)